<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  AppStream metadata for Wayfinder Aura
  Validate with: appstreamcli validate io.wayfindercollective.WayfinderAura.metainfo.xml
-->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.wayfindercollective.WayfinderAura</id>

  <name>Wayfinder Aura</name>
  <summary>Local-first voice dictation — speak, text appears at your cursor</summary>

  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>Elastic-2.0</project_license>

  <developer id="io.wayfindercollective">
    <name>Wayfinder Collective</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Wayfinder Aura is a local-first voice dictation application for Linux. Press a hotkey,
      speak, and your words are typed wherever your cursor is. By default, transcription runs
      on your device with whisper.cpp — in local mode your voice never leaves your computer.
      Optional cloud transcription backends are available if you choose to enable them, and the
      app checks online for model updates (toggleable).
    </p>
    <p>
      Free tier includes local whisper.cpp dictation, hotkeys, text injection, and the full
      settings UI. Wayfinder Aura Ultra is an optional one-time purchase (launch price $29.99;
      regular price $60) that unlocks GPU acceleration, larger models, longer recording sessions,
      advanced audio options, and other premium features. Ultra is sold on wayfindercollective.io
      (not through Flathub billing); enter a license key in Settings after purchase.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Local-first &amp; Private — transcribed on your device by default; optional cloud backends if you choose them</li>
      <li>Hotkey Triggered — Press a key to start/stop recording</li>
      <li>Wayland &amp; X11 Support — Works on modern Linux desktops</li>
      <li>System Tray Integration — Runs quietly in the background</li>
      <li>Multiple Whisper Models — Choose speed vs accuracy (tiny → large)</li>
      <li>Smart Cleanup — Optional local LLM polishes grammar and tone</li>
      <li>Game Aware — Hotkeys pause automatically while a game is running</li>
      <li>Configurable Typing Speed — Instant paste or simulated typing</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Perfect for writing emails, documents, code comments, chat messages, or any
      situation where speaking is faster than typing.
    </p>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.wayfindercollective.WayfinderAura.desktop</launchable>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Dictate into any app — hotkey recording with live waveform feedback</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wayfindercollective/wayfinder-aura/main/screenshots/main-window.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Private local processing — microphone and audio settings on free tier</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wayfindercollective/wayfinder-aura/main/screenshots/settings.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Live recording status with reactive waveform while you speak</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wayfindercollective/wayfinder-aura/main/screenshots/overlay.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Tone-aware cleanup — Minimal, Professional, Casual, Dev, and more</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wayfindercollective/wayfinder-aura/main/screenshots/style.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Guided first run — calm three-step welcome tour</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wayfindercollective/wayfinder-aura/main/screenshots/welcome.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/wayfindercollective/wayfinder-aura</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/wayfindercollective/wayfinder-aura/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/wayfindercollective/wayfinder-aura</url>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#4682DC</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#2F6BC4</color>
  </branding>

  <categories>
    <category>Utility</category>
    <category>Accessibility</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>voice</keyword>
    <keyword>dictation</keyword>
    <keyword>speech</keyword>
    <keyword>whisper</keyword>
    <keyword>transcription</keyword>
    <keyword>speech-to-text</keyword>
    <keyword>accessibility</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <provides>
    <binary>wayfinder-aura</binary>
  </provides>

  <requires>
    <display_length compare="ge">360</display_length>
  </requires>

  <supports>
    <control>pointing</control>
    <control>keyboard</control>
  </supports>

  <releases>
    <release version="1.1.2" date="2026-07-16">
      <description>
        <p>Tag CI hardening for AppImage smoke and release packaging</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Tolerate modern AppStream tags on older ubuntu-22.04 appstreamcli</li>
          <li>glslc_exe + glslang-tools for AppImage native builds</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.1" date="2026-07-16">
      <description>
        <p>Flathub submission packaging release</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Sandbox-friendly model download paths (no host home filesystem grants)</li>
          <li>Clear free-tier vs Ultra pricing disclosure in store metadata</li>
          <li>Stable storefront checkout alias for Ultra purchase</li>
          <li>CI and packaging hardening for public Flatpak builds</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="1.1.0" date="2026-07-07">
      <description>
        <p>First public release of Wayfinder Aura</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Press Super+F2 to dictate — your words appear at the cursor in any app</li>
          <li>Local-first transcription with whisper.cpp; optional tone cleanup on-device</li>
          <li>Works on Wayland and X11, including KDE and GNOME</li>
          <li>Game-aware hotkeys pause while a GameMode game is running</li>
          <li>Steam Deck workflow: bind a back button and dictate from Game Mode</li>
          <li>System tray integration and configurable typing speeds</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
